{
  "translations": {
    "en": {
      "grammar": {
        "type": "multiple",
        "description": "One way to describe a language is in the form of a <b>grammar</b>. Below is a grammar that describes a really small subset of the English language.",
        "question":"What is a grammar?",
        "answer": "A way to describe languages",
        "choices": ["A way to describe languages", "A way to spell sentence right", "A way to arrange words in sentences"]
      },
      "terminal": {
        "type": "select",
        "description": "Any grammar has <b>variables</b> (also called <b>non-terminals</b>) and <b>terminals</b>. Terminals are generally strings. Variables are things that ultimately are replaced by terminals. In our example grammar, the variables are in brackets $\\lt \\gt$. (We won't always use brackets around variables for every example, though.)",
        "question": "Which of these are terminals?",
        "answer": ["a", "ball", "hit"],
        "choices": ["$\\lt noun\\gt$", "a", "ball", "$\\lt verb\\gt$", "hit"],
        "correctFeedback": ["Variables have brackets. Terminals do not."],
        "incorrectFeedback": ["Variables have brackets. Terminals do not."]
      },
      "nonterminal": {
        "type": "select",
        "description": "Any grammar has <b>variables</b> (also called <b>non-terminals</b>) and <b>terminals</b>. Terminals are generally strings. Variables are things that ultimately are replaced by terminals. In our example grammar, the variables are in brackets $\\lt \\gt$. (We won't always use brackets around variables for every example, though.)",
        "question": "Which of these are variables (non-terminals)?",
        "answer": ["$\\lt noun\\gt$", "$\\lt verb\\gt$"],
        "choices": ["$\\lt noun\\gt$", "a", "ball", "$\\lt verb\\gt$", "hit"],
        "correctFeedback": ["Variables have brackets. Terminals do not."],
        "incorrectFeedback": ["Variables have brackets. Terminals do not."]
      },
      "production": {
        "type": "select",
        "description": "Grammars have a collection of productions. Productions are separated by '|'. In this example, each production replaces a variable with some series of variables and terminals.",
        "question": "The $\\lt d.o.\\gt$ variable has two productions associated with it. Which are they?",
        "answer": ["$\\lt article\\gt\\lt noun\\gt$", "$\\lt noun\\gt$"],
        "choices": ["$\\lt article\\gt\\lt noun\\gt$", "$\\lt noun\\gt$", "$\\lt d.o.\\gt$", "$\\lt subject\\gt$", "Fritz", "$\\lt article\\gt$", "$\\lt noun\\gt | \\lt noun\\gt$"]
      },
      "start":{
        "type": "multiple",
        "description": "All sentences in the language are generated by starting with the $\\lt sentence\\gt$ variable and using productions to reach the desired sentence.",
        "question":"Which variable must we start with?",
        "answer": "$\\lt sentence\\gt$",
        "choices": ["$\\lt sentence\\gt$", "$\\lt subject\\gt$", "$\\lt verb\\gt$", "$\\lt d.o.\\gt$", "$\\lt article\\gt$", "$\\lt noun\\gt$"]
      },
      "sentence": {
        "type": "multiple",
        "description": "You can form only certain sentences using the language",
        "question": "Which sentence belongs to this language?",
        "answer": "the ball hit the Fritz",
        "choices": ["the hit ball Fritz", "the ball hit the Fritz", "the Fritz hit ran", "ran Fritz"],
        "correctFeedback": ["See if you can determine which series of productions were used to generate this sentence when starting at $\\lt sentence\\gt$."],
        "incorrectFeedback": ["There is no way to start with $\\lt sentence\\gt$ and replace each variable through production rules to reach this sentence."]
      },
      "first":{
        "type": "multiple",
        "description": "We are now going to show how to <b>derive</b> a sentence from the grammar, beginning with the start variable and using a series of productions. The sentence is 'Fritz hit the ball'. The first step is to replace $\\lt sentence\\gt$ with the only production available: $\\lt subject\\gt\\lt verb\\gt\\lt d.o.\\gt$. The next steps will replace these variables in turn.",
        "question":"What is the substitute for $\\lt subject\\gt$ to derive the sentence ‘Fritz hit the ball’?",
        "answer": "$\\lt noun\\gt$",
        "choices": ["$\\lt sentence\\gt$", "$\\lt noun\\gt$", "$\\lt article\\gt$", "$\\lt article\\gt\\lt noun\\gt$", "Fritz"],
        "correctFeedback": ["$\\lt subject\\gt$ has two productions to chose from, but only one of them can lead to a sentence that starts with 'Fritz'."]
      },
      "Fritz":{
        "type": "multiple",
        "description": "We used the symbol $\\rightarrow$ to indicate that a substitution takes place. So far, we have $\\lt sentence\\gt\\ \\rightarrow\\ \\lt subject\\gt\\lt verb\\gt\\lt d.o.\\gt\\ \\rightarrow\\ \\lt noun\\gt\\lt verb\\gt\\lt d.o.\\gt$.",
        "question": "What is the substitute for $\\lt noun\\gt$ to derive the sentence 'Fritz hit the ball'?",
        "answer": "Fritz",
        "choices": ["$\\lt sentence\\gt$", "$\\lt noun\\gt$", "$\\lt article\\gt$", "$\\lt article\\gt\\lt noun\\gt$", "Fritz"]
      },
      "verb":{
        "type": "multiple",
        "description": "Now we have 'Fritz $\\lt verb\\gt\\lt d.o.\\gt$'. Continue substituting variables.",
        "question":"What is the substitute for $\\lt verb\\gt$ to derive the sentence 'Fritz hit the ball'?",
        "answer": "hit",
        "choices": ["hit", "ran", "ate", "ball", "the"]
      },
      "do":{
        "type": "multiple",
        "description": "Now we have 'Fritz hit $\\lt d.o.\\gt$'. Continue substituting variables.",
        "question":"What is the substitute for $\\lt d.o.\\gt$ to continue deriving the sentence 'Fritz hit the ball'?",
        "answer": "$\\lt article\\gt\\lt noun\\gt$",
        "choices": ["$\\lt article\\gt\\lt noun\\gt$", "$\\lt noun\\gt$", "the", "ball", "the ball"]
      },
      "article":{
        "type": "multiple",
        "description": "Now we have 'Fritz hit $\\lt article\\gt\\lt noun\\gt$'. Continue substituting variables.",
        "question":"What is the substitute for $\\lt article\\gt$ to derive the sentence 'Fritz hit the ball'?",
        "answer": "the",
        "choices": ["the", "ate", "ball", "the ball", "an"]
      },
      "noun":{
        "type": "multiple",
        "description": "Last step! Now we have 'Fritz hit the $\\lt noun\\gt$'.",
        "question":"What is the substitute for $\\lt noun\\gt$ to derive the sentence `Fritz hit the ball'?",
        "answer": "ball",
        "choices": ["ran", "ate", "ball", "an", "a"]
      },
      "bad":{
        "type": "multiple",
        "description": "The final derivation is: $\\lt sentence\\gt\\ \\rightarrow\\ \\lt subject\\gt\\lt verb\\gt\\lt d.o.\\gt\\ \\rightarrow\\ \\lt noun\\gt\\lt verb\\gt\\lt d.o.\\gt\\ \\rightarrow\\ $ Fritz $\\lt verb\\gt\\lt d.o.\\gt\\ \\rightarrow\\ $ Fritz hit $\\lt d.o.\\gt\\ \\rightarrow\\ $ Fritz hit $\\lt article\\gt\\lt noun\\gt\\ \\rightarrow\\ $ Fritz hit the $\\lt noun\\gt\\ \\rightarrow\\ $ Fritz hit the ball.",
        "question":"Can we derive these two sentences? 'The ball hit Fritz' or 'The ball ate the ball'?",
        "answer":"Yes",
        "choices": ["Yes", "No"]
      },
      "syntax":{
        "type": "multiple",
        "description": "The reason why we can derive “The ball hit Fritz”, and “The ball ate the ball” is that grammars only focus on the correct <b>syntax</b>.",
        "question":"Can grammars generate sentences with bad <b>semantics</b> (they are meaningless)?",
        "answer":"Yes",
        "choices": ["Yes", "No"]
      },
      "leftside":{
        "type": "select",
        "description": "The formal definition for a grammar is $G = (V, T, S, P)$ where $V$ is a finite set of variables (nonterminals), $T$ is a finite set of terminals (generally, these are strings), $S$ is the start variable $(S \\in V$), and $P$ is a set of productions (rules) of the form $x \\rightarrow y$. This means to replace $x$ by $y$",
        "question":"What does $x$ represent?",
        "answer":["Variables", "Terminals"],
        "choices": ["Variables", "Terminals"],
        "correctFeedback": ["It might seem strange that $x$ can include both variables and terminals. But we will see later on that certain types of grammars can be quite flexible."]
      },
      "rightside":{
        "type": "select",
        "description": "The formal definition for a grammar is $G = (V, T, S, P)$ where $V$ is a finite set of variables (nonterminals), $T$ is a finite set of terminals (generally, these are strings), $S$ is the start variable $(S \\in V$), and $P$ is a set of productions (rules) of the form $x \\rightarrow y$. This means to replace $x$ by $y$",
        "question":"What does $y$ represent?",
        "answer":["Variables", "Terminals"],
        "choices": ["Variables", "Terminals"],
        "correctFeedback": ["It should be no surprise that the right-hand side of a production can contain a mix of variables and terminals."]
      },
      "parts":{
        "type": "select",
        "description": "What is the language of the grammar? Answer: It is all strings formed from the set of terminals ($T^∗$ is all possible strings over $T$), such that if you start with $S$ (the start symbol for the grammar), then you can derive the string.",
        "question":"Consider the grammar: $G = (\\{S\\},\\ \\{a,b\\},\\ S,\\ P)$, where $P=\\{S \\rightarrow aaS,\\ S \\rightarrow b\\}$. What is $S$?",
        "answer":["Start Variable", "Variables"],
        "choices": ["Variables", "Terminals", "Start Variable", "Grammar Production Rules"]
      },
      "parts2":{
        "type": "select",
        "description": "What is the language of the grammar? Answer: It is all strings formed from the set of terminals ($T^∗$ is all possible strings over $T$), such that if you start with $S$ (the start symbol for the grammar), then you can derive the string.",
        "question":"Consider the grammar: $G = (\\{S\\},\\ \\{a, b\\},\\ S,\\ P)$, where $P=\\{S \\rightarrow aaS,\\ S \\rightarrow b\\}$. What is $\\{a, b\\}$?",
        "answer":["Terminals"],
        "choices": ["Variables", "Terminals", "Start Variable", "Grammar Production Rules"]
      },
      "LG":{
        "type": "select",
        "description": "What is the language of the grammar? Answer: It is all strings formed from the set of terminals ($T^∗$ is all possible strings over $T$), such that if you start with $S$ (the start symbol for the grammar), then you can derive the string.",
        "question":"Consider the grammar: $G = (\\{S\\},\\ \\{a, b\\},\\ S,\\ P)$, where $P=\\{S \\rightarrow aaS,\\ S \\rightarrow b\\}$. What does $L(G)$ mean?",
        "answer":["The language represented by the grammar"],
        "choices": ["The language represented by the grammar", "The grammar"]
      },
      "G":{
        "type": "select",
        "description": "What is the language of the grammar? Answer: It is all strings formed from the set of terminals ($T^∗$ is all possible strings over $T$), such that if you start with $S$ (the start symbol for the grammar), then you can derive the string.",
        "question":"Consider the grammar: $G = (\\{S\\},\\ \\{a, b\\},\\ S,\\ P)$, where $P=\\{S \\rightarrow aaS,\\ S \\rightarrow b\\}$. What is $G$?",
        "answer":["The grammar"],
        "choices": ["The language represented by the grammar", "The grammar"]
      },
      "LGlist":{
        "type": "select",
        "description": "What is the language of the grammar? Answer: It is all strings formed from the set of terminals ($T^∗$ is all possible strings over $T$), such that if you start with $S$ (the start symbol for the grammar), then you can derive the string.",
        "question":"Consider the grammar: $G = (\\{S\\},\\ \\{a, b\\},\\ S,\\ P)$, where $P=\\{S \\rightarrow aaS,\\ S \\rightarrow b\\}$. What is $L(G)$?",
        "answer":["$\\{b, aab, aaaab, ... \\} = \\{(aa)^nb\\ |\\ n \\ge 0\\}$"],
        "choices": ["$\\{b, aab, aaaab, ... \\} = \\{(aa)^nb\\ |\\ n \\ge 0\\}$", "$\\{ab, aaab, aaaaab, ... \\} = \\{a(aa)^nb\\ |\\ n \\ge 0\\}$", "$\\{bb, aabb, aaaabb, ... \\} = \\{(aa)^nbb\\ |\\ n \\ge 0\\}$"]
      },
      "whichrules":{
        "type": "select",
        "description": "What is the language of the grammar? Answer: It is all strings formed from the set of terminals ($T^∗$ is all possible strings over $T$), such that if you start with $S$ (the start symbol for the grammar), then you can derive the string.",
        "question":"Consider $L(G) = \\{a^nccb^n\\ |\\ n > 0\\}$. Which of the following sets of productions rules derive $L(G)$?",
        "answer": ["$P = \\{S \\rightarrow aSb\\ |\\ aAb,\\ A \\rightarrow cc\\}$", "$P = \\{S \\rightarrow aSb\\ |\\ accb\\}$", "$P = \\{S \\rightarrow aSb\\ |\\ B,\\ B \\rightarrow aAb,\\ A \\rightarrow cc\\}$"],
        "choices": ["$P = \\{S \\rightarrow aSb\\ |\\ aAb,\\ A \\rightarrow cc\\}$", "$P = \\{S \\rightarrow aSb\\ |\\ accb\\}$", "$P = \\{S \\rightarrow aSb\\ |\\ B,\\ B \\rightarrow aAb,\\ A \\rightarrow cc\\}$"]
      },
      "pickstrings":{
        "type": "select",
        "description": "What is the language of the grammar? Answer: It is all strings formed from the set of terminals ($T^∗$ is all possible strings over $T$), such that if you start with $S$ (the start symbol for the grammar), then you can derive the string.",
        "question":"Consider grammar $G = (\\{S\\},\\ \\{a,b\\},\\ S,\\ P)$, where $P = \\{S \\rightarrow aSb,\\ S \\rightarrow SS,\\ S \\rightarrow ab\\}$. Which of the following strings are in $L(G)$?",
        "answer":["$aabb$", "$abab$"],
        "choices": ["$aabb$", "$abab$", "$abba$", "$babab$"]
      },
      "whatlang":{
        "type": "multiple",
        "description": "What is the language of the grammar? Answer: It is all strings formed from the set of terminals ($T^∗$ is all possible strings over $T$), such that if you start with $S$ (the start symbol for the grammar), then you can derive the string.",
        "question":"Consider grammar $G = (\\{S\\},\\ \\{(, )\\},\\ S,\\ P)$, where $P = \\{S \\rightarrow (S),\\ S \\rightarrow SS,\\ S \\rightarrow ()\\}$.<br/>[T/F] This grammar represents the language of matching parentheses.",
        "answer":["True"],
        "choices": ["True", "False"]
      }
    }
  }
}
